ILGWU Mid-West Region Records 5780/101
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Mid-West Region Records
1909-1996
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU)
5780/101
3.83 cubic feet
3.8 linear ft.
Records (documents).
The collection contains charters, correspondence, agreements, printed material, and memorabilia of the office of the Midwest Region of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Two series of correspondence (one alphabetical, another chronological) and collective bargaining agreements constitute the bulk of the collection. Several Midwest Region local unions are represented in the records: 5, 18, 59, 76, 100, 191, 240, 261, 272, 303, 326, 336, 337, 355, 373, 395, 436, 442, 455, 488, 505, 527.
5516146
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
T. Dean, June 11, 2009
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 11, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
From its earliest years, the ILGWU was involved in organizing women's garment workers in Chicago, and efforts to gain members in the city and throughout the Midwest continued throughout the union's existence. The Midwest Region represented workers in Chicago and much of Illinois, Indiana, Wisconsin, Michigan, and Iowa.
Morris Bialis was the ILGWU's longtime representative in the Midwest, Manager of the Chicago Joint Board, and the Midwest Region Director from 1922 to 1976. Harold Schwartz served as regional director from 1976 to 1978. Schwartz was succeeded by Lou Montenegro, who held the post until his retirement in 1990. Stanley Gross was Midwest Region Director at the time of the ILGWU's merger with ACTWU in 1995.
Scope and Contents
The majority of the collection is composed of material that is of a political nature. The contents help to illustrate the role of politics within the ILGWU at the regional level. Much of the collection is organized by individuals, mainly Congressional candidates for House Districts and Senate seats within the locals of states from the Midwest Region, such as Michigan, Indiana, and particularly Illinois. The majority of the material includes campaign letters and correspondence from Congressional candidates as they reached out for support from labor within their districts. Often, the communication involves the political education directors, Evelyn Dubrow, executive secretary of the Political Department for the ILGWU, and Frank Klein of the Political Department for the ILGWU Midwest Region. Some of the subjects and topics contained in the records is material from the Governor campaign for Illinois; correspondence with Congressmen who opposed NAFTA; ILGWU funded campaigns; clippings from races in key legislative districts; mayors; fundraiser dinners and events; campaign contributions from the union; and correspondence regarding election results or legislation passed. Beyond regional and local political matters, information can also be found on a national level, including presidential campaigns.
Another component of the collection encompasses memos and letters that originated from the office of the Midwest Region Director, Stanley Gross. The remainder of the collection consists of collective bargaining agreements between locals and various garment shops and apparel companies, often for different years. Locals from the Midwest included in agreements are: 76, 261, 272, 120, 337, 382, 449, 455, 471, 499, 517, 336-K, 343, 488, 314, 186, 468, 543, 459, 529, 551, 443, and 317. Additionally, there are local handbooks and by-laws, as well as informational pamphlets.
The collection also contains oversize material of original charters for the following locals:
81 Cloak and Suit Cutters Union of Chicago, 1911
18 Chicago Cloak and Suit Pressers Union, 1914
59 Cloak, Suit and Dress Finishers' Union (Chicago), 1920
261 Blouse, Skirt, Pajamas and Bathrobe Workers' Union (Chicago), 1936
436 De Kalb IL 1946
240 Aurora IL, 1936
76 White Goods Workers of Chicago, 1933
Chicago Joint Board consisting of locals 5, 18, 59, 81, 100 on 1961
5 Cloakmakers Union of Chicago, 1909
Midwest District Council composed of locals 76, 261, 191, 240, 303, 336, 372, 436, 529, 272, 505, 5, 81, 100, 326, 337, 355, 395, 442, 455, 488 on 1980
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/101 AV: ILGWU Mid-West Region Audio-Visual Materials
Women's clothing industry -- United States.; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States.; Clothing workers -- United States.; Industrial relations -- United States.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. -- Midwest Region.
5516146
- Bob Anderson for Congress: 11th Congressional District, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Clem Balanoff, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Thomas Barret, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Evan Bayh, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Peter Barca, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Rod Blagojevich, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- David Bonior, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- John F. Boyd, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Braun, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Carol Mosley Braun, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Jerry Brown Camp, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Senator Terry Bruce, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Roland Burris, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Roland Burris, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Mayor Jane Byrne, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Honorable David E. Clarenbach, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Cardiss Collins, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Carr for Congress, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Clinton, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Jimmy Carter, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- John J. Cullerton, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Richard M. Daley, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Danny K. Davis, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Torch Light Parade, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Miguel Del Valle, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Vince Demuzio Committee, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Alan Dixon, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Robert J. Dole: U.S. Senate, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Scope and Contents
  June 7, 1982
- Durbin Congress: Democrat, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Jim Edgar: Secretary of State, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Jim Edgar, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Lane Evans, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Tim Evans, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Honorable William A. Ford, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- John Fray, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Feingold, Russell, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Fithian For U.S. Senate, 1982-1992 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Russ Feingold, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Flanagan, Rep. Michael, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Friends of Labor Decatur, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Jesus Garcia, 1986-1996 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Jesus Garcia, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Senator Charles Grassley, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  August 8, 1996
- Ken Gray, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  October 1, 1986
- Senator John Glenn, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Luis Gutierrez, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Luis Gutierrez, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Tom Hecht, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  July 21, 1994
- Adeline J. Geo-Karis: Illinois State Senate, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  July 12, 1982
- Mike Harmless, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Charles Hayes, 1984-1992 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Neil Hartigan: Attorney/General/Illinois, 1988-1995 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Charles Hartke, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Congressman Henry Hyde, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Hogsett for Senate, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Honorable Joseph Hogsett: Hoosiers for Hogsett, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  April 27, 1992
- Jesse Jackson, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Aaron Jaffe, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Jones, Jr. Emil: Senate Minority Leader, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Nancy Kaszak, 1992-1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Mary Lou Kearns for Congress 1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Edmund Kelly, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  June 18, 1986
- Kildee Congressman, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Senator Herb Kohl, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Jerry Kleczka, 1994-1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Kohl, Herb, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  January 27, 1994
- Robert T. Krska: State Representative, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  May 7, 1982
- Edward Kennedy, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  October 28, 1987
- Alan Lanning, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  September 16, 1980
- Gary Lapaille, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  April 16, 1991
- Lautenschlager, Peg, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  September 9, 1992
- Ellis Levin, 1980-1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Tom Lindley for Congress, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Lipinski for Congress, 1982-1995 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Lombard Improvement Party, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Illinois AFL-CIO: State's Legislative Elections, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  August 13, 1996
- Michael J. Madigan, 1982-1996 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Michael Madigan, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Lou Montenegro: Memo's To, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Spanish
- Martin, Lynn, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  October 19, 1992
- John Matigevich, 1982-1988 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Committee to Elect Ben Martinez, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Congressman John Conyers, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- McCloskey for Congress, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  November 9, 1982
- Jim McPike, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Jim McPike, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Abner J. Mikva, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Mondale for President Campaign, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Walter Mondale Campaign '1984' (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Labor Rally for Mondale, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Munoz, Ricardo, 1993-1996 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Dave Nagle, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- David Orr, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  October 5, 1994
- Alderman David Orr, 1987-1994 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Alice Palmer, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- O'Malley, Jack, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Cecil Partee, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Charles Percy, 1978-1984 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Charles Percy, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Perot, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Phelan, Richard, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Robert Platner, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Mayor John Porcelli, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  June 26, 1984
- Porter, John: Rep., 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Roman Pucinski, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Glenn Poshard, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- Aurelia Pucinski, 1984-1992 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- Aurelia Pucinski, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Patrick Quinn, 1984-1996 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Dan Rostenkowski, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Reynolds, Mel, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 53)
- President Ronald Reagan, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Donald Riegle, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- David Robinson, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Phil Rock, 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Alfred Ronan, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 58)
- Edward J. Roswell, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 59)
- Dan Rostenkowski, 1980-1993 (Box 2, Folder 60)
- Bobby Rush, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 61)
- Marty Russo, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  March 2, 1992
- Marty Russo, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 63)
- George Ryan, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  May 15, 1981
- George E. Sangemeister for Congress Committee, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  October 14, 1992
- Gus Savage: Member of Congress, 1982-1989 (Box 2, Folder 66)
- Jan Schakowsky, 1986-1995 (Box 2, Folder 67)
- Shiller, Helen, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  January 20, 1995
- Stephen Schiller, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 69)
- Shaw, William, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  January 4, 1994
- Sonia Silva, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 71)
- Paul Simon, 1983-1993 (Box 2, Folder 72)
- Seymour Simon for Justice Committee, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 73)
- Margaret Smith, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  May 12, 1983
- Citizens for Jeff Smith, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 75)
- 11th Ward, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  January 22, 1990
- Paul Simon: U.S. Senate, 1983-1996 (Box 2, Folder 77)
- Paul Simon: Women's Committee, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 78)
- Jeff Smith, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 79)
- Juan Soliz, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 80)
- Juan Soliz, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 81)
- Lydia Spotswood for Congress (Wisconsin State AFL-CIO), 1996 (Box 2, Folder 82)
- Penny Severns, 1989-1994 (Box 2, Folder 83)
- Aldai E. Stevenson, 1982-1987 (Box 2, Folder 84)
- January 1993, Memos (Box 3, Folder 1)
- February 1993: Letters (Box 3, Folder 2)
- March 1993: Letters (Box 3, Folder 3)
- April 1993: Letters (Box 3, Folder 4)
- May, 1993: Letters (Box 3, Folder 5)
- June, 1993: Letters (Box 3, Folder 6)
- June, 1993: Letters (Box 3, Folder 7)
- August, 1993: Letters (Box 3, Folder 8)
- September, 1993: Letters (Box 3, Folder 9)
- October, 1993: Memos (Box 3, Folder 10)
- November, 1993: Memos (Box 3, Folder 11)
- December 1993: Memos (Box 3, Folder 12)
- January, 1994: Letters (Box 3, Folder 13)
- February 1994: Letters (Box 3, Folder 14)
- March, 1994: Letters (Box 3, Folder 15)
- April, 1994: Memos (Box 3, Folder 16)
- May, 1994: Letters (Box 3, Folder 17)
- June, 1994: Letters (Box 3, Folder 18)
- July, 1994: Letters (Box 3, Folder 19)
- August, 1994: Letters (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Yates for Congress Committee, 1982-1990 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Wolpe for Congress, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Jesse White, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  April 6, 1983
- Patrick Welch, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  August 28, 1992
- Weinberger for Congress, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Harold Washington, 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Harold Washington - Rally for Justice, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Mayor Sawyer, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Visclosky, Peter, 1993-1996 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- 37th Ward Regular Democrat Organization, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- James R. Thompson, 1984-1989 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Information on 1986 Cope Gubernatorial Endorsement (Box 3, Folder 32)
- James Thompson, 1978-1988 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Honorable Bart Stupak's, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  October 30, 1992
- Stupak, Bart, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- John Stroger, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- G. Douglas Stephens, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Eugene Sawyer, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Mayor Washington, 1983-1992 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Mayor Washington, 1983-1987 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Aldai Stevenson, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Aldai Stevenson, 1978-1982 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Aldai Stevenson, 1982-1986 (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Aldai Stevenson, 1978-1982 (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Aldai Stevenson, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 45)
- ILGWU: Sing-A-Long, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 46)
- AFL-CIO Songbook, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Agreement Between Garment Industries of Illinois and International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Agreement Between Herrin Division of Dresseteria, Inc. and International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Agreement Between K Mart Apparel Service of Des Plaines Corp. and The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 50)
- Agreement Between Monmouth Division of Prattville Apparel Co., Inc. and International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Agreement Between the Garment Industries of Illinois and the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 52)
- Contract of Local Number 488 International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (Box 3, Folder 53)
- Agreement Between Presbyterian-St. Luke's Hospital and Hospital Employees Labor Program of Metropolitan Chicago, 1967-1970 (Box 3, Folder 54)
- Agreement Between Lincoln Division of Prattville Apparel Co., Inc. and the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 55)
- Agreement Between Johnnye Manufacturing Company and International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 56)
- Agreement Between Salem Manufacturing Company and The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 57)
- Agreement Between Fairfield Garment Company and International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 58)
- Agreement Between Eldorado Apparel Company and International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 59)
- Dressmakers' Union Handbook for Price Settlements (Box 4, Folder 1)
- By-Laws of Local Union (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Agreement Between Garment Industries of Illinois and Midwest Region Great Lakes States District Council No. 1, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Collective Bargaining Agreement Between K Mart Apparel Service of Des Plaines Corp. and the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Agreement Between Chicago Trading Corp. and the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Agreement by and Between Mattoon Garment Company and International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Agreement Between R. & M. Kaufmann, Inc. and International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Agreement Between Joan-Claire, Inc. and International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Agreement Between Mt. Carmel Apparel Company and International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Agreement and Wage Schedule Between Mt. Carmel Garment Co., and International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Agreement Between Mt. Carmel Apparel Company and International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Agreement Between the Wolverine Knitting Mills, Inc. and International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1981-1983 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- How to Run a Union Meeting, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- What Can You Do About Problems at Work? (Box 4, Folder 14)
- What is the Labor School? (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Working People are Winning Jobs with Justice, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- District Counsel Meeting Minutes, 1984-1995 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Agreements of the Join Board Cloakmakers' Union with Industrial Council, Merchants' Association, American Association, Infants' and Childrens' Coat Association, 1937-1970 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Directory of Massachusetts Legislators, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Unite in Massachusetts: Political Action Manual, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union Certificates, 1911-1946 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union: Local No. 240 Certificate, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union: Local Union No. 76 Certificate, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union: Local Union Numbers 5, 18, 59, 81, 100 Certificate, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  January 13, 1961
- International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union: Local Union No. 5 Certificate, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  December 20, 1909
- International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union: Local Union Numbers; 76, 261, 191, 240, 303, 336, 372, 436, 527, 272, 505, 5, 81, 100, 326, 337, 355, 395, 442, 455 and 488 Certificate, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  March 3, 1980